

Abhijit Mishra

Research Scientist IBM Research AI, Bangalore, India +918879006045 abhijimi@in.ibm.com https://abhijitmishra.github.io

ABOUT ME

I am currently a part of IBM Research AI, Bangalore, India, serving as Research Scientist in the division of AI-Tech. I am involved in multiple projects based on Natural Language Generation (NLG), viz., (1) Controllable Text Transformation (2) Structured Data Summarization, and (3) Devising evaluation metrics for quality estimation of NLG Output.

Prior to joining IBM Research, I was a Ph.D. student in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay (graduated in 2017). I was advised by Prof. Pushpak Bhattacharyya for my research on *Cognitive NLP* which aims to (i) uncover the cognitive underpinnings of human language processing and (ii) translate the insights into better language processing systems. For this purpose, *Eye-Tracking technology* was employed to record and analyze human eye movement patterns to gain insights into the human way of performing Translation, Sentiment and Sarcasm Analysis, and tackling linguistic subtleties during reading

Apart from thesis related work, I contributed to various projects related to Machine Translation, Social Media Text Analysis, Crowdsourcing and Development of Resources and Tools for Indian Language Processing.

APPOINTMENTS

Research Scientist

Mar 2017-

IBM Research AI, Bangalore, India

- Department: AI Tech
- Current Focus: Systems and services involving Natural Language Generation

Teaching Assistant through Project

July 2011-Mar 2017

IIT Bombay, Mumbai, India

- Project 1: Cognitive NLP Harnessing Cognitive Information for Natural Language Processing- An Investigation based on Eye-tracking (Thesis Project)
- Project 2: Shata-Anuvaadak (100 Translators) A Multilingual Machine Translation Framework for Indian Languages
- Project 3: Generation of Multilingual Resources for Indian Language Processing through Crowdsourcing
- Project 4: A Computational Approach to Automatic Prediction of Drunk Texting

Visiting Researcher

June 2012-Aug 2012

Copenhagen Business School, Denmark

- Research Topic: Eye Tracking Applications in Translation Process Research
- Analyzed translator's activity collected in the form of eye-movement and keystroke patterns

• Correlated complexity of eye movement patterns, believed to be an indicator of perceived complexity, with linguistic subtleties of the translated text

Assistant System Engineer

August 2010-June 2011

Tata Consultancy Services Limited, Bangalore India

- Role: Developer for Allianz-USA client
- Developed and supported a module for automatically managing documents using Java, VB Script, HTML-CSS

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Computer Science and Engineering

2011-2017

Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, Mumbai, India

"Harnessing Cognitive Information for Natural Language Processing: An Investigation based on Eyetracking"

Thesis advisor: Pushpak Bhattacharyya, Professor, Dept. of C.S.E, IIT Bombay

B.Tech. Computer Science and Engineering

2006-2010

College of Engineering and Technology, Bhubaneswar, India CPI 9.03 (out of 10)

PUBLICATIONS

Main Conference

- 14. Vitobha Munigala, Abhijit Mishra, Srikanth Govindaraj Tamilselvam, Shreya Khare, Riddhiman Dasgupta and Anush Sankaran. 2018. PersuaAIDE! An Adaptive Persuasive Text Generation System for Fashion Domain. WWW 2018, Lyon, France, 23th April 27th April, 2018
- 13. <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Srikanth Tamilselvam, Riddhiman Dasgupta, Seema Nagar and Kuntal Dey. 2018. Cognition-Cognizant Sentiment Analysis with Multitask Subjectivity Summarization based on Annotators' Gaze Behavior. **AAAI 2018**, New Orleans, USA, 2nd February 7th February, 2018
- 12. Srikanth Tamilselvam, Seema Nagar, Abhijit Mishra and Kuntal Dey. 2017. Graph Based Sentiment Aggregation using ConceptNet Ontology. IJCNLP 2017, Taipei, Taiwan, 27 November-1st December, 2017
- 11. Shweta Garg, Sudhanshu S Singh, Abhijit Mishra and Kuntal Dey. 2017. CVBed: Structuring CVs using Word Embeddings. IJCNLP 2017, Taipei, Taiwan, 27 November-1st December, 2017
- Joe Cheri Ross, <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Kaustuv Kanti Ganguli and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2017.
 Identifying Raga Similarity Through Embeddings Learned from Compositions' Notation. IS-MIR 2017, Suzhou, China, 23-28 October, 2017
- 9. Abhijit Mishra, Kuntal Dey and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2017. Learning Cognitive Features from Gaze Data for Sentiment and Sarcasm Classification using Convolutional Neural Network. ACL 2017, Vancouver, Canada, 30 July-4 August, 2017

- 8. Abhijit Mishra, Diptesh Kanojia, Seema Nagar, Kuntal Dey, Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2017. Scanpath Complexity: Modeling Reading Effort using Gaze Information. AAAI 2017, San Francisco, USA, 4-9 February, 2017
- Abhijit Mishra, Diptesh Kanojia, Seema Nagar, Kuntal Dey and Pushpak Bhattacharyya.
 Harnessing Cognitive Features for Sarcasm Detection. ACL, 2016, Berlin, Germany,
 August, 2016
- 6. <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Diptesh Kanojia, Kuntal Dey, Seema Nagar and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2016. *Leveraging Cognitive Features for Sentiment Analysis*. **CoNLL 2016**, Berlin, Germany, August 11-12, 2016
- 5. Abhijit Mishra, Diptesh Kanojia and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2016. Predicting Readers' Sarcasm Understandability by Modelling Gaze Behaviour. AAAI 2016, Phoenix, USA, Feb 12-17, 2016
- 4. Aditya Joshi, <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Balamurali AR, Pushpak Bhattacharyya, Mark J Carman. 2015. A Computational Approach for Automatic Prediction of Drunk-texting. **ACL 2015**, Beijing, China, July 2015
- 3. Aditya Joshi, Abhijit Mishra, Nivvedan Senthamilselvan and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2014. Measuring Sentiment Annotation Complexity of Text. ACL 2014, Baltimore, USA, 23-25 June, 2014
- 2. Anoop Kunchukuttan, Abhijit Mishra, Rajen Chatterjee, Ritesh Shah and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2014. Shata-Ānuvadak: Tackling Multiway Translation of Indian Languages. **LREC 2014**, Rekjyavik, Iceland, 26-31 May, 2014
- Abhijit Mishra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2013. Automatically Predicting Sentence Translation Difficulty. ACL 2013, Sofia, Bulgaria, 4-9 August, 2013

Workshop and System Papers

- 8. Parag Jain, Priyanka Agrawal, Abhijit Mishra, Mohak Sukhwani and Anirban Laha. 2017. Story Generation from Sequence of Independent Short Descriptions. ML4Creativity, SIGKDD Workshop, Halifax, Nova Scotia Canada, 2017
- Joe Cheri, Abhijit Mishra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2016. Leveraging Annotators' Gaze
 Behaviour for Coreference Resolution. ACL 2016 Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of
 Computational Language Learning (CogACLL 2016) at ACL 2016, Berlin, Germany,
 August 11, 2016
- 6. Diptesh Kanojia, Shehzaad Dhuliawala, Abhijit Mishra, Naman Gupta and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2015. TransChat: Cross-Lingual Instant Messaging for Indian Languages. ICON 2015. December 2015
- 5. Abhijit Mishra, Aditya Joshi and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2014. A cognitive study of subjectivity extraction in sentiment annotation., 5th Workshop on Computational Approaches to Subjectivity, Sentiment and Social Media Analysis (WASSA 2014), Baltimore, USA, 27 June, 2014

- 4. Anoop Kunchukuttan, Ratish Pudupully, Rajen Chatterjee, <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2014. The IIT Bombay SMT System for ICON 2014 Tools Contest. NLP Tools Contest at ICON 2014 (ICON 2014), Goa, India, Dec 2014
- 3. Piyush Dungarwal, Rajen Chatterjee, <u>Abhijit Mishra</u>, Anoop Kunchukuttan, Ritesh Shah and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2014. The IIT Bombay Hindi-English Translation System at WMT 2014. 9th Workshop on **Statistical Machine Translation** (WMT14), Baltimore, USA, 26-27 June, 2014
- Anoop Kunchukuttan, Rajen Chatterjee, Shourya Roy, <u>Abhijit Mishra</u> and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2013. TransDoop: A Map-Reduce based Crowdsourced Translation for Complex Domain. ACL 2013, Sofia, Bulgaria, 4-9 August, 2013
- Abhijit Mishra, Michael Carl and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2012. A Heuristic Based Approach
 for Systematic Error Correction of Gaze Data for Reading. First Workshop on Eye Tracking
 and NLP, part of COLING 2012. Mumbai, India, 15 Dec, 2012

BOOK (UPCOMING)

• Abhijit Mishra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya, "Cognitively Inspired Natural Language Processing", Monograph, Springer (Tentative Month of Publication: May, 2018)

FEDERAL FUNDING

- Cognitive Science Research Initiative Scheme, Department of Science and Technology (Govt. of India), for research on Cognitive Natural Language Processing based on Eye-tracking and EEG (INR 40 Lacs, PI Prof. Pushpak Bhattacharyya)
- Research Infrastructure Funding Scheme, IIT Bombay for Cognitive NLP Lab Setup (INR 42 Lacs, PI Prof. Pushpak Bhattacharyya)

TUTORIALS AND INVITED TALKS

- 20 Jan, 2018: Tutorial on "Natural Language Generation", Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India
- 31 Jul, 2017: Talk on paper "Learning Cognitive Features from Gaze Data for Sentiment and Sarcasm Classification using Convolutional Neural Network", ACL 2017 Conference, Vancouver, Canada
- 08 Aug, 2016: Presentation on "Harnessing Cognitive Features for Sarcasm Detection.", ACL 2016 Conference, Berlin, Germany
- 20 June 2016: Tutorial on "Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning", VIVA Institute of Technology, Mumbai, India
- 21 Jan, 2015: Talk on "Cognitive NLP", IIT Bombay (Target Audience: Visiting Team, NIST, USA)

- 10 Jul, 2014 18 Jul, 2014: Tutorial on "Natural Language Processing", Samsung Research Lab, Bangalore
- 28 Nov, 2013: Talk on "Eye Tracking Applications in Translation Process Research", JSS Academy of Science, Noida, India
- 10 Aug, 2013: Talk on "Estimation of Text Translation Complexity", Copenhagen Business School, Copenhagen, Denmark

AWARDS AND RECOGNITIONS

- Recipient of IBM Ph.D. Fellowship award for the academic year of 2015-2016
- Recipient of Institute level, department level conference travel grants and Microsoft Travel Grant to attend ACL 2013, ACL 2016 and AAAI 2016 conferences
- Received Regional Runner-Up Award for the region India and South-east Asia in the global Windows 7 Coding contest (Code 7 contest-2009) organized by Microsoft Corporation for developing a gesture based interactive human computer interface that can run on any Windows based system with a low cost web-camera

ACADEMIC SERVICES

- Program committee member for ACL 2018, LREC 2018 ACL 2017, COLING 2016, NAACL 2016, ICON (2014, 2015, 2016, 2017)
- Organizing committee member, COLING 2012, Mumbai, India
- Co-supervised Nivvedan S. (C.S.E., IIT Bombay, 2014), Shubham S. (C.S.E., IIIT Allahabad, 2014), and Krishna G. (C.S.E., IIT Bombay, 2017) for their B.Tech. Thesis Projects
- Teaching Assistant for Natural Language Processing Course (CS 626-460), Autumn, 2014

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Programming Languages: Python, C, C++, Java, Perl, HTML and CSS
- Language processing and machine learning tools: PyTorch and Keras for Deep Learning, NLTK, Stanford Core NLP tool, Moses Statistical Machine Translation Toolkit, Weka, Scikit-learn
- Eye-tracking/EEG devices and tools: SR research Eyelink 1000, Tobii eye-tracking systems, Translog-II-eye tracking tool (developed some portions of this tool), Biosemi EEG

PERSONAL DETAILS

Date of Birth: 3rd March, 1989

Permanent Address: S/O- Bibhuti Bhusan Mishra, Matiapada, Puri -2, Odisha

Languages Known: Odia, English, Hindi and German (basic)